These days, the only AI agents that
people seem to care about anymore are AI
coding assistants. No one seems to cover
anymore building agents with LangChain
or n8n or Pydantic AI. If you follow
mainstream YouTube or LinkedIn, it just
seems like these frameworks don't matter
anymore. And honestly, I've kind of
fallen into this camp myself. I used to
cover all the time building agents with
Pydantic AI and n8n and the OpenAI
agents SDK, building local AI agents. I
was all about this, but then my channel
has definitely shifted a lot more
towards just using AI coding assistants
effectively. That's just what is the
most relevant right now. And a lot of
these coding agents have released SDKs,
so we can build our own agents on top of
all the power they give us out of the
box. And so there's this big narrative
right now that we don't need these
frameworks anymore. Let's just build
everything on top of the Claude agent
SDK. And that is actually kind of true
for some use cases. For these,
everything you thought about building AI
agents needs to be thrown out of the
window. But then for other use cases,
this isn't true at all. So there's a lot
of nuance that we have to cover here. If
you look at all of the business use
cases out there with the billions of
agents that are being built, a lot of
them, maybe even a majority, are still
being built on top of these more classic
use cases. But then some are
transitioning. It's making more sense to
just build them right on top of these
SDKs. So I want to cover this nuance
with you. When it makes sense to build
on top of the SDKs, when it makes sense
to use a framework. There are some other
important evolutions we have to talk
about as well, like relying a lot more
on skills now and different ways of
performing rag. I want to cover all this
and make the decisions very easy for
you. All right, so let's start by
talking about the old way of building AI
agents. A lot of this still applies, but
every agent was built this way in 2024
and 2025. So you'd start by picking your
framework. All of these are valid.
There's honestly way too many options
out there, but you just pick the one
that you're the most comfortable with or
your organization uses. And then you
define the tools for your agent, all the
capabilities, like searching through a
file system, accessing your inbox, that
kind of thing. And then from there, this
isn't a hard requirement, but most AI
agents, especially back then, had some
kind of rag. So you define your chunking
embedding and retrieval strategy for
your agent to search through a knowledge
base. And then finally, you would wire
up the agent loop, so state and memory
management, things like short-term
memory, being able to store all your
conversations in a database. And of
course, I got some examples here to go
with everything that I'm talking about
in the diagram. So I'll link to this
repo in the description. I want to start
here with like the most classic rag
agent ever. Not that these ideas have
gone away, but this is just how we would
see almost every single agent defined in
2024 and 2025. So you'd start with your
agent definition using a framework like
Pydantic AI. You define your model, your
system prompt, the tools, like this is a
tool to search our knowledge base with
rag, cuz rag was in almost every single
agent. So you'd have your chunking
strategy and your embedding strategy and
your ingestion pipeline. There was a lot
of code here. And so within our
database, like I love using Neon for my
Postgres database. I still do for a lot
of my agents. We have our documents here
and then we have our chunks, a lot of
chunks. We'd manage all of our messages
and sessions. Everything what for our
agent was managed in our own database.
This is the way that it was done before
all of the time. Now the point I'm
trying to make here is a lot of times
that is still necessary, but there is a
lot of glue code to create the agent
infrastructure ourselves. There is a lot
of complexity there. And so a lot of
people are shifting over to using the
batteries included SDKs. So building
non-coding agents on top of a coding
agent foundation with something like the
Claude agent SDK or the Codex SDK. And
the beauty of using this as a starting
point is there's a ton of prompting and
tools that are built into the solution
for us already. And they manage the
conversation history for us. So we don't
even have to store that part in our
database. So it just gives us a
launching pad. We have support for
skills and MCP servers. Those are the
newer ways to build tools into our
agents as well. And so it's not that
you'll use these all of the time. And
I'll cover that in just a second here,
but it's so much easier to build agents
on top of these SDKs versus doing it the
old way, building with one of these
frameworks. Take a look at how simple
and powerful this is. Now I have my
entire AI agent using the Claude agent
SDK in a single TypeScript file. And
instead of defining my own AI agent, I
just call right into Claude code and I
define all of my options, like the tools
that it's allowed to use, so the ones
that I want to leverage that are built
right into the SDK. Also, I have
sub-agents that I have defined here. So
we're adding in a lot more than we
didn't even have in the other agent, MCP
servers. I can build my own custom
tools. So instead of defining the tools
directly into our agent, we can create
them as MCP servers, so they're a lot
more reusable. We can do the same thing
with skills. I have skills built into
this agent as well, so it can generate
PowerPoints for me. There's actually
more built into this agent and it's less
code overall. We don't even need the rag
pipeline and everything because for a
lot of these Claude agent SDK agents,
you're just going to rely on the file
search capabilities built right into the
SDK. We can have hooks, we can set the
permissions, we can build our own system
prompt. We have everything that we had
before and more. And if I really wanted
to use rag still, and we might, I'll
talk about that in a little bit as well,
we can just include that through skills
and MCP servers. So I hope you can see
how powerful it is to use these SDKs. It
simplifies things so much for us because
we're building on top of these tools
that are powerful. There's so much
attention going to these coding agents
for a reason. And this is exactly what
I'm using for my second brain. So I'm
using the Claude agent SDK for the whole
heartbeat system that I built for my own
second brain inspired by Open Claw. It
handles all my integrations and
everything I wanted it to take care of.
It builds memories over time. It does
daily reflection to basically learn from
its work and my requests over time. This
entire thing is using the Claude agent
SDK, which by the way, if you're
interested in learning how I've built my
second brain using the Claude agent SDK
and Claude code, I'm hosting a 4-hour
workshop in my Dynamis community.
Friday, April 3rd at 11:00 a.m. Central
Time. So if you want [snorts] to save
yourself hours and hours every single
week building a second brain on top of
Claude code, definitely come be a part
of the community and join me for this
workshop. And building a second brain
with the Claude agent SDK is just one of
many very powerful use cases. However,
there are some big limitations with
these batteries included SDKs. This is
what's going to lead us into the
importance of still building a lot of
our agents with these frameworks. So
three key limitations that I want to
hone in on with you right now. The first
one is that these SDKs are significantly
slower than what you can build with
these frameworks. And the reason for
that is there's a lot of reasoning
overhead because there's so much built
into these SDKs out of the box for you.
So the convenience of having all these
tools and support for things like
sub-agents and skills and the prompting
that's already there for you, like all
that makes it very easy to work with
these tools, but it means that you're
coming into building your agent with
something that's already a bit bloated.
And that also makes it more token heavy.
And so these two very much go hand in
hand. And then it's also a bit more
non-deterministic because there's a lot
of things that are managed for you. So
it's non-deterministic in the sense that
you don't get to define exactly how your
agent operates quite as much. When we're
building with a framework, we're more
building from the ground up. So any kind
of use case where speed or cost or
utmost flexibility is extremely
important, that's when you want to build
on top of a framework like Pydantic AI.
I'm still using Pydantic AI all of the
time. Building with these frameworks is
what's going to allow you to build
agents with sub-second response times,
the most flexibility possible because
you're controlling everything, even the
conversation history. For a lot of these
production agents where you need a lot
of observability and control, like being
able to store the message history
yourself and manage that yourself, you
can't be using something like the Claude
agent SDK cuz that's just not an option
for you. Now besides the obvious speed
difference between the frameworks and
the SDKs, there's one other big reason
why most of the time when you have an
agent deployed to production, it's going
to use a framework instead of the SDK.
And it is all about cost. Like we talked
about earlier, these SDKs are very token
heavy. So most of the time when you use
them, you're going to be using your
subscription, like your Anthropic
subscription or your OpenAI
subscription. But you're only allowed to
use your subscription when it is just
you interacting with the agent.
Otherwise, it is a violation of the
terms of service for any of these SDK
platforms. And so if you have multiple
people using your agent in production,
you have to use your API key. You have
to pay an obscene amount for API costs.
So that's really another limitation for
these SDKs here. So that's why I usually
use a framework. It's going to be a lot
more cost-effective. You can really use
it at scale and not worry about burning
millions and millions of tokens. And
using these frameworks, you still do
have the ability to include all these
modern techniques like skills and MCP
servers. So it might be a bit more work
to set it up, but it's still very
realistic. And let me show you this with
an example, actually. One of the things
you might think is missing out of the
box for these agent frameworks is
support for skills. And so that's the
main way to give capabilities to our
coding agents now, and we're just
starting to see it added into these
agent frameworks. And so, what I did,
I'll link to a video right here where I
covered this more in-depth, is I created
a Pydantic AI agent where I added in my
own support for skills. So, you have
your skills directory here with all your
skill.md files. Everything works the
exact same as it would in in Claude
Code, but now we have our own custom
agent where we have full control. It's
going to be a lot faster and more token
efficient. And so, this setup looks
pretty similar to the very first RAG
agent example that I gave. We define the
model, the system prompt, the tool set
here, but the tools are more about
loading the skills now. This is the most
modern way to add capabilities into our
AI agent. So, we have a dynamic system
prompt where I basically describe to the
agent, "Here are your available skills."
And I load it dynamically from the
skills directory, and then the rest of
the system prompt is just describing to
the agent how to leverage these skills.
And so, for example, going into the
agent right here, I just have a simple
CLI. I can say, "What is the weather in
New York?"
And just like Claude Code, this agent is
able to call a tool to load the skill.
So, it brings in the skill.md which
gives it instructions for how to make
the API calls, and then we get the
current weather in New York. But, take a
look at how fast that was. That would be
take at least 10 seconds to get an
answer from the Claude Asian SDK just
because of how bloated it is. And so,
it's very easy to build any capability
you need into your own agents,
especially with the help of AI coding
assistance now. So, sometimes you just
want something out of the box, the
Claude Asian SDK is great. Other times
you need that speed and scalability, and
it's not going to be that difficult to
use a coding agent to help you build
this all yourself. I use Claude Code to
help me build this Pydantic AI agent.
So, with all that context setting the
stage, I now want to cover the super
simple decision framework for you.
Should you go with an SDK or a
framework? So, we'll talk about this,
and then I'll get into RAG because
that's really the last component that I
haven't hit on too much that I said was
a part of the old way. It's still
relevant, but then also some strategies
with existing tools that replace it.
We'll talk about that in a second. But,
for the decision framework here, it
really just comes down to two questions
to ask yourself. Who is going to use
your agent, and what is your tolerance
for things like speed and scale? If it
is just you using the agent and some
delay is okay, you don't need to scale,
then I would highly recommend going with
the Claude Asian SDK or Code X SDK.
Something out of the box that gives you
a ton of power, and you have to worry
about less of the infrastructure. But,
if a lot of other people are using your
agent, you're deploying it to a
production platform, it needs to scale
and be fast, then you still should go
with, you know, the classic way of using
a framework like Pydantic AI or
LangGraph. And in the end, you do want
to just start with the simplest
implementation. So, you won't go the
other way, but sometimes you'll start
with the Claude Asian SDK just to test
some tooling through skills or MCP, and
then you would transition to a Pydantic
AI agent once you need to scale. So,
there is a little bit of like you can
try with both, but usually this decision
is going to make it very obvious for you
right when you're starting with your use
case. So, I hope this decision framework
is helpful for you. The last thing I
want to talk about is what happened to
RAG? Why are so many coding agents and
other agents not using traditional RAG
as the default playbook anymore? A lot
of people are saying that RAG is dead.
want to clarify this for you right now.
So, in 2024, no one really questioned
RAG. Pretty much every single agent was
using semantic search as a way to access
external information. But then in 2025,
people started to question this because
we were relying a lot more on file
search. Coding agents especially stopped
using vector databases, they're using
tools like grep now. That's why we see
all of this built directly into the
SDKs. For smaller corpuses of knowledge,
it was proven last year that file search
actually outperforms RAG or classic
semantic search. Llama Index did a
study, Claude Code, a lot of these
coding agents switching away. A lot of
that was pointing towards the direction
of RAG is dead. But, there's a lot more
nuance to this than people realize
because for larger knowledge bases with
thousands of documents, semantic search
is still more accurate and way, way
cheaper. And so, now we've kind of
gotten to a middle ground this year with
agentic RAG. We give our agent the
ability to perform both semantic search
and other kinds of searches like grep
and keyword search. Graph RAG is really
popular as well, especially especially
for massive codebases or projects with
many different codebases. So, at an
enterprise level,
RAG is still used for AI coding. And
then for most AI agents, we still need
RAG to access our knowledge bases. File
search is not enough. It's a good
starting point, and it works better for
smaller knowledge bases, but you still
need that for a lot of your agents. For
a lot of my AI agents, I'm still
spending a good amount of time in my
database trying different RAG
strategies, building around semantic
search. Even with the Claude Asian SDK,
building semantic search through skills
and MCP servers. And Second Brains are a
good demonstration of this. I've built
mine on top of the Claude Asian SDK, but
I use both of the capabilities built
right in, and then also I have my own
RAG setup that's actually inspired by
OpenClaude, also built in for semantic
search. So, to summarize everything
here, match your tool for your use case.
There are a million use cases that are
great for the SDKs, and just as many if
not more where you want to use a
framework and build it more from the
ground up. And I hope this decision
framework has made it really easy for
you to think about that for your own AI
agents. And so, if you found this
helpful, and you're looking forward to
more things on building AI agents and
agentic coding, I would really
appreciate a like and a subscribe. And
with that, I will see you in the next
video.